

GRADUATE STUDENT

they · them · theirs

□ (+1) 512 963-9951 | ■ jumfowle@ucsc.edu.edu | # https://julesfowler.github.io/ | 🖸 julesfowler | ♥ @121gigajules | orcid: 0000-0002-0726-9323

Summary .

Astronomer: NSF Fellow researching exoplanets, adaptive optics, and high contrast imaging.

Software Engineer: Python and Git expert, Linux enthusiast.

Instructor: Software Carpentry Instructor and Python training developer.

Activist: member of the AAS committee for Sexual and Gender Minorities in Astronomy.

Research Experience ____

Lab for Adaptive Optics (LAO)

Santa Cruz, CA

University of California, Santa Cruz

Sept. 2020 - PRESENT

- Designing a Lyot and Vortex coronagraph for upcoming high contrast imaging test bench in the LAO.
- Simulating a design study for adaptive primaries with mid-sized (2 meter class) telescopes.
- Characterizing a custom Spatial Light Modulator to simulate phase errors introduced by ground based atmospheric turbulence.
- Building SEALpup, a coronagraph in a box outreach demo based on the Santa Cruz Extreme AO Lab testbed.
- Advisor: Rebecca Jensen-Clem

Russell B. Makidon Optics Lab

Baltimore, MD

SPACE TELESCOPE SCIENCE INSTITUTE (STSCI)

Oct. 2018 - Sept. 2020

- Principal Investigator of the Generalized Lab Architecture for Restructured Optical Experiment (G.L.A.R.E.) an STSCI Director's Discretionary Research project to build autonomous experiment software and hardware controllers for optics experiments.
- Wrote fully-automated target acquisition and Python control software for nPoint tip/tilt controller as part of an optics testbed for LUVIOR-like coronagraphy experiments.
- Advisors : Rémi Soummer & Marshall Perrin

Exoplanet Characterization Toolkit

Baltimore, MD

STSCI May 2017 - Jan. 2020

- Developed first on-the-fly observation planning tool for exoplanet transits with JWST (the James Webb Space Telescope.)
- · Built an HDF5 database and web interface for the Goyal et. al. (2018) grid of forward model transmission spectra.
- · Advisors: Kevin Stevenson & Nikole Lewis

Space Telescope Advanced Research Group for the Atmospheres of Transiting Exoplanets

Baltimore, MD

STScI

Oct. 2017 - Oct. 2018

- Wrote open source pipeline to reduce WFC3/IR spatial scan slitless spectroscopy data, fit transit parameters with a Markov-Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC), calculate Bayesian statistics, and produce transmission spectra.
- Advisors: Hannah Wakeford & Jeff Valenti

Wide Field Camera Three Instrument Team

Baltimore, MD

STScI

Aug. 2016 - Jan. 2020

- Lead of the WFC3 Quicklook project, developing automated monitors and calibration software on a large-scale web and database application.
- Principal Investigator of eleven HST calibration proposals.
- Created user guides and tools for WFC3/IR slitless spectroscopy data reduction and anomaly tracking.
- · Advisors: Elena Sabbi & Sylvia Baggett

Tufts University Somerville, MA

SUMMER SCHOLAR & SENIOR THESIS

May 2015 - July 2016

- Compared energy contribution of low energy radio jets to gas outflows in AGN.
- Used slurm parallel cluster computing and CASA to reduce a terrabtye of multi-band Very Large Array (VLA) data.
- Received High Honors for senior thesis detailing analysis and small numbers statistics.
- Advisor: Anna Sajina

University of Texas, Austin

Austin, TX

RESEARCH INTERN May 2012 - August 2013

- Performed stellar evolution and structure research on Betelgeuese and Wolf-Rayet stars.
- Created computational models using ${\tt MESA}$ star.
- · Advisor: Craig Wheeler

1

Education

University of California, Santa Cruz

GRADUATE STUDENT

Santa Cruz, CA September 2020 - PRESENT

• Graduate Student in Astronomy and Astrophysics

Tufts University Somerville, MD

B.S. Astrophysics & Philosophy

- · Graduated with High Thesis Honors.
- Dean's List 2013, 2015

Sept. 2012 - May 2016

Dealt's List 2013, 2013

Space Telescope Science Institute

Work Experience

Baltimore, MD

SCIENCE SOFTWARE ENGINEER

Aug. 2016 - Sept. 2020

- · Member of the Wide Field Camera Three Instrument Team and involved with multiple science projects across the institute.
- Started SpaceGAYs, the first LGBT+ affinity group at STScI, and member of the Invision Diversity Working Group.
- Designed Advanced Python training with outside vendor, and gave SWC inspired introductory Python and Git training.

Exoplanet Exploration Program "ExoExplorers" Inaugural Cohort, seminar series and scholarship to

Tufts University, Department of Physics and Astronomy

Somerville, MA

TEACHING ASSISTANT & TUTOR

Sept. 2014- July 2016

- Lab TA for introductory mechanics and class TA for general audience astronomy seminar.
- · Tutored individual students and led study groups for introductory physics, calculus, and linear algebra.
- Assisted students with accessible exam accommodations.

Grants & Awards_

GRANTS

2021	develop early career exoplanet scientists	Pasadena, CA
2021	University of California Osterbrock Grant, small project grants to encourage leadership and outreach	
	projects led by astronomy graduate students	Santa Cruz, CA
2020	National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellowship, 3 year NSF fellowship for exemplary	
	graduate students in STEM	
2020	University of California Regents Fellowship, 1 year University of California wide fellowship for graduate	Santa Cruz, CA
	students	Santa Cruz, CA
2019	STScI Data Science Innovation Initiative Grant, Director's Discretionary Research Fund call for projects	Baltimore, MD
	with a focus on data science and interesting computational problems	baltimore, MD
2015	Tufts Summer Scholar Grant, call for summer long indepedent research projects	Somerville, MA
2015	Tufts Center for Stem Diversity Grant , grant to create the first collegiate queer science speaker series	Somerville, MA
AWARDS	5	
2019	STScI Achievement Award, team award for teaching GitHub and Python to colleagues at STScI	Baltimore, MA
2019	STScI Achievement Award, team award for contributing to the Exoplanet Characterization Tool Kit	Baltimore, MA
2016	Tufts University Pride on the Hill, for contributions to LGBT+ climate	Somerville, MA
2015	Tufts Multicultural Service Award, for contributions to diversity efforts	Somerville, MA
Comi	nittees	
2019	Inclusive Astronomy II, member of the Science Organizing Committee	Baltimore, MD
2019	STScI/AURA Exoplanet Astronomer hiring committee, member	Baltimore, MD
2019	STScI Information Technology Head hiring committee, member	Baltimore, MD
2018	AAS Committee for Sexual and Gender Minorities in Astronomy (SGMA), member	
2016	out in STEM (oSTEM) @ Tufts, president and founder	Somerville, MA
2015	Tufts Society of Physics Students , president	Somerville, MA
2014	Tufts Queer Students Association, treasurer	Somerville, MA

2

Certifications & Skills

Certified SCRUM Master SCRUM Alliance

Certified Software Carpentry Instructor Software Carpentry

Laser Safety Certification Laser Institute of America

Python, Git, conda, bash, Linux, Mac OS, Windows, LaTeX expert

Mathematica, Markdown, HTML advanced

C, MATLAB, Julia, IDL, IRAF/PyRAF, JacaScript, CSS beginner

Teaching _____

Software Carpentry at the AAS

remote / Seattle, WA

INSTRUCTOR Jan. 2021, Jan. 2019

Astronomy focused Python and bash at the 237TH and 233RD AAS meeting.

Everything you needed to know about JWST Exoplanet Transit Data: How to Plan, Reduce, and Fit your data with the Exoplanet Characterization Toolkit Workshop

Honolulu, HI

INSTRUCTOR Jan. 2020

• Submitted proposal for and led an ExoCTK workshop at the 235th AAS meeting.

We Brought a Coronagraph to a Bar!

Baltimore, MD

Spring 2016

PRESENTER Jun. 2019

• Astronomy on Tap talk with interactive Lyot coronagraph demo.

Software Carpentry at the New York Academy of Sciences

New York, NY

INSTRUCTOR Jan. 2019

• Taught general science focused Python and Git at NYAS.

Tufts University Concepts of the Cosmos Somerville, MA

CLASS TA

Tufts University Physics 1 & Physics 11 Somerville, MA

LAB TA Fall 2015

• Lab TA for the introductory mechanics courses with and without calculus.

• Class TA for the introductory/general education astronomy seminar.

Publications and Presentations

JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

Disentangling the Planet from the Star in Late-Type M Dwarfs: A Case Study of TRAPPIST-1g

Wakeford, H.; Lewis, N.; **Fowler, J.**; Bruno, G.; Wilson, T.; Moran, S. E.; Valenti, J.; Batalha, N.; Filippazzo, J.; Bourrier, V.; Hörst, S.; Lederer, S. M.; De Wit, J.

The Astronomical Journal, Volume 157, Issue 1, article id. 11, 14 pp. (2019)

The Betelgeuse Project: constraints from rotation

Wheeler, J.; Nance, S.; Diaz, M.; Smith, S.; Hickey, J.; Zhou, L.; Koutoulaki, M.; Sullivan, J.; Fowler, J. Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, Volume 465, Issue 3, p.2654-2661, (2017)

STScI Instrument Publications

Analyzing Eight Years of Transiting Exoplanet Observations Using WFC3's Spatial Scan Monitor

STEVENSON, K.; FOWLER, J.

Instrument Science Report WFC3 2019-12, 16 pages

WFC3/UVIS Gain Stability Results for Cycles 24 and 25

FOWLER, J.

Instrument Science Report WFC3 2018-17, 24 pages

The Cosmic Ray That Wouldn't Quit: Correcting Cosmic Rays in Overscan Pixels

FOWLER, J

Instrument Science Report WFC3 2017-12, 7 pages

Monitoring the WFC3/UVIS Relative Gain with Internal Flatfields

FOWLER, J.; BAGGETT, S.

Instrument Science Report WFC3 2017-08, 17 pages

Analysis of Dragon's Breath and Scattered Light Detector Anomalies on WFC3/UVIS

FOWLER, J.; MARKWARDT, L.; BOURQUE, M.; ANDERSON, J.

Instrument Science Report WFC3 2017-02 (v.1), 14 pages

PRESENTATIONS

The Generalized Lab Architecture for Restructured Optical Experiments (GLARE)

poster winter, 2020

FOWLER, J.; NOSS, J.; LAGINJA, I.; SOUMMER, R.; PERRIN, M. American Astronomical Society, AAS Meeting #235

Standardizing Exoplanet Analysis with the Exoplanet Characterization Tool Kit (ExoCTK)

talk

FOWLER, J.; STEVENSON, K.; LEWIS, N.; FRAINE, J.; PUEYO, L.; BRUNO, G.; FILIPPAZZO, J.; HILL, M.; BATALHA, N.; WAKEFORD,

summer, 2018

American Astronomical Society, AAS Meeting #232

Advances on Hubble Wide Field Camera 3 Grism Calibration and Slitless Spectroscopy **Analysis**

poster

FOWLER, J.; BRAMMER, G.; RYAN, R.; DEUSTUA, S.; PIRZKAL, N.

winter, 2018

American Astronomical Society, AAS Meeting #231, id. 355.19 The Exoplanet Characterization ToolKit (ExoCTK)

poster

STEVENSON, KEVIN; FOWLER, J.; LEWIS, N.; FRAINE, J.; PUEYO, L.; VALENTI, J.; BRUNO, G.; FILIPPAZZO, J.; HILL, M.; BATALHA,

winter, 2018

American Astronomical Society, AAS Meeting #231, id. 148.14

Do Radio Jets Contribute to Driving Ionized Gas Outflows in Moderate Luminosity Type 2

poster

FOWLER, J.; SAJINA, A.; LACY, M.

winter, 2016

American Astronomical Society, AAS Meeting #227, id.243.08